Present AddressBerlin, Germany

Anjo Vahldiek-Oberwagner

Contact Info

anjovahldiek@gmail.com Phone: +49 173 154 88 46 https://vahldiek.github.io

INTERESTS

I'm interested in tackling hard problems by analyzing, designing, building, and evaluating the security, performance, and usability of hardware and software systems. My current research focuses on building secure systems including techniques protecting data confidentiality and integrity of sensitive data at rest, inflight or in-memory.

EXPERIENCE

Adjunct Lecturer at TUM

July'22 – now

At Distributed & Operating Systems Chair

Research Scientist at Intel Labs

April'19 – now

Intel Labs - Datacenter Security Group, Hillsboro, OR (2019-2022) → Berlin (starting 2022)

Research and develop security technologies. Build prototypes and guide technology transfers.

Current focus: Building confidential compute cloud-native prototypes, and memory isolation techniques improving security, performance, and usability of cloud workloads. Working on

open-source projects (e.g., initial developer of <u>Gramine Shielded Containers</u>). Established 7 academic collaborations and transfer technology into Intel products and open-source projects (e.g., <u>WAMR</u>).

Research Software Engineering Intern

Summer 2014

Microsoft Research, Redmond, WA

Research opportunities to overcome performance and flexibility issues with Trusted Platform Modules (TPM) using Intel's new Software Guard Extension (SGX). Build and evaluate a prototype implementation.

Software Engineering Intern/Bachelor Thesis

2006 - 2009

IBM, Boeblingen, Germany & Austin, Texas, USA

Analyzed, designed and implemented prototypes. Optimizing Informix Dynamic Servers (IDS), programming models for heterogeneous processor architectures.

EDUCATION

Ph.D. Candidate co-advised by Peter Druschel & Deepak Garg

2010 - 2019

Max Planck Institute for Software Systems, Saarbruecken, Germany

Ph.D. Candidate mentored by Holger Hermanns

2009 - 2010

Saarland University, Graduate School, Saarbruecken, Germany

Bachelor of Science in Applied Computer Science

2006 - 2009

Baden-Württemberg Cooperative State University Stuttgart (DHBW Stuttgart) with IBM Germany

Thesis: "Distributed Complex Query Processing for Informix Dynamic Server"

GPA: 1.5 (scale 1.0 to 5.0), First Class, Top 10%

SKILLS

C, Java, Python, Operating Systems, Secure System Design, Distributed Systems, Storage Systems, Trusted Computing, SSD/Flash Memory, Linux, Memory Safety and Isolation

PUBLICATIONS

Complete list: Google Scholar

Top Venues: USENIX Security (3), EuroSys (2), ASPLOS(1), CCS (1), OSDI (1), IEEE S&P (1)

Endoprocess: Programmable and Extensible Subprocess Isolation

Fangfei Yang, Weijie Huang, Kelly Kaoudis, Anjo Vahldiek-Oberwagner, Nathan Dautenhahn

NSPW 2023

Trusted Heterogeneous Disaggregated Architectures

Atsushi Koshiba, Felix Gust, Julian Pritzi, Anjo Vahldiek-Oberwagner, Nuno Santos, Pramod Bhatotia

APSys Workshop 2023

Going beyond the Limits of SFI: Flexible and Secure Hardware-Assisted In-Process Isolation with HFI

Shravan Narayan, Tal Garfinkel, Mohammadkazem Taram, Joey Rudek, Evan Johnson, Anjo Vahldiek-

Oberwagner, Michael LeMay, Ravi Sahita, Dean Tullsen, Deian Stefan

ASPLOS 2023, Distinguished Paper Award

uSWITCH: Fast Kernel Context Isolation with Implicit Context Switches

Dinglan Peng, Congyu Liu, Tapti Palit, Pedro Fonseca, Anjo Vahldiek-Oberwagner, Mona Vij

IEEE Security & Privacy 2023

Segue & ColorGuard: Optimizing SFI Performance and Scalability on Modern x86

Shravan Narayan, Tal Garfinkel, Evan Johnson, David Thien, Joey Rudek, Michael LeMay, Anjo Vahldiek-

Oberwagner, Dean Tullsen, Deian Stefan

PLAS Workshop 2022

MeSHwA: The case for a Memory-Safe Software and Hardware Architecture for Serverless Computing

Anjo Vahldiek-Oberwagner, Mona Vij

WORDS Workshop 2022

Cerberus: A Formal Approach to Secure and Efficient Enclave Memory Sharing

Dayeol Lee, Kevin Cheang, Alexander Thomas, Catherine Lu, Pranav Gaddamadugu, Anjo Vahldiek-

Oberwagner, Mona Vij, Dawn Song, Sanjit A Seshia, Krste Asanović

ACM CCS 2022

Expanding the Scope of Artifact Evaluation at HPC Conferences: Experience of SC21

Tanu Malik, Anjo Vahldiek-Oberwagner, Ivo Jimenez, Carlos Maltzahn

P-RECS Workshop 2022

The Endokernel: Fast, Secure, and Programmable Subprocess Virtualization

Bumjin Im, Fangfei Yang, Chia-Che Tasi, Michael LeMay, **Anjo Vahldiek-Oberwagner**, Nathan Dautenhahn arXiv 2021

Swivel: Hardening WebAssembly against Spectre

Shravan Narayan, Craig Disselkoen, Daniel Moghimi, Sunjay Cauligi, Evan Johnson, Zhao Gang, Anjo Vahldiek-

Oberwagner, Ravi Sahita, Hovav Shacham, Dean Tullsen, Deian Stefan

USENIX Security 2021

Tutorial: Graphene: Confidential Computing for Unmodified Linux Applications

Anjo Vahldiek-Oberwagner, Chia-Che Tsai, Dmitrii Kuvaiskii, Don Porter

IEEE Secure Development Conference (SecDev), 2020

Privacy-Preserving Machine Learning in Untrusted Clouds Made Simple

Dayeol Lee, Dmitrii Kuvaiskii, **Anjo Vahldiek-Oberwagner**, Mona Vij arXiv 2020

ERIM: Secure, Efficient In-process Isolation with Memory Protection Keys

Anjo Vahldiek-Oberwagner, Eslam Elnikety, Nuno O. Duarte, Michael Sammler, Peter Druschel, Deepak Garg USENIX Security 2019

Distinguished Paper Award and Internet Defense Prize 2019

Techniques to Protect Confidentiality and Integrity of Persistent and In-Memory Data

Anjo Vahldiek-Oberwagner

PhD Thesis 2019

PESOS: Policy Enhanced Secure Object Store

Robert Krahn, Bohdan Trach, **Anjo Vahldiek-Oberwagner**, Thomas Knauth, Pramod Bhatotia, Christof Fetzer **ACM EuroSys 2018**

Light-Weight Contexts: An OS Abstraction for Safety and Performance

James Litton, **Anjo Vahldiek-Oberwagner**, Eslam Elnikety, Deepak Garg, Bobby Bhattacharjee, Peter Druschel **USENIX OSDI 2016**

Thoth: Comprehensive Policy Compliance in Data Retrieval Systems

Eslam Elnikety, Aastha Mehta, Anjo Vahldiek-Oberwagner, Deepak Garg, Peter Druschel

USENIX Security 2016

Guardat: Enforcing data policies at the storage layer

Anjo Vahldiek-Oberwagner, Eslam Elnikety, Aastha Mehta, Peter Druschel, Deepak Garg, Rodrigo Rodrigues, Johannes Gehrke, Ansley Post

ACM EuroSys 2015

Protecting Data Integrity with Storage Leases

Anjo Vahldiek, Eslam Elnikety, Ansley Post, Peter Druschel, Rodrigo Rodrigues

Technical Report 2011-08, MPI-SWS, 2011 & granted patent

A Verified Dependable Wireless Safety Critical Hard Real-Time Design

Hernan Baro Graf, Holger Hermanns, Juhi Kulshrestha, Jens Peter, **Anjo Vahldiek**, Aravind Vasudevan **IEEE WoWMoM 2011**

Evaluation of an Optimization for Object Tracking – Feedback-Based Head-Tracking

Anjo Vahldiek, Ansgar Schneider, Stefan Schubert, Dirk Reichard

Fifth Annual Meeting on Information Technology and Computer Science of the Baden-Wuerttemberg Cooperative State University, 2009

Patents Granted: 2 Applications: 8

US Patent App. 18 / 311,253 (2023): Method and apparatus for multi-dimensional attestation for a software application

Marcela S Melara, Bruno Vavala, Michael Steiner, Vincent Scarlata, Anjo Lucas Vahldiek-Oberwagner

US Patent 11,650,800 (2023): Attestation of operations by tool chains

Vincent Scarlata, Alpa Trivedi, Reshma Lal, Marcela S Melara, Michael Steiner, Anjo Vahldiek-Oberwagner

US Patent App. 17/710,723 (2022): Scalable cloning and replication for trusted execution environments Ravi Sahita, Dror Caspi, Vedvyas Shanbhogue, Vincent Scarlata, **Anjo Lucas Vahldiek-Oberwagner**, Haidong Xia, Mona Vij

US Patent App. 17/481,405 (2022): Cryptographic computing including enhanced cryptographic addresses Michael D LeMay, David M Durham, **Anjo Lucas Vahldiek-Oberwagner**, Anna Trikalinou

US Patent App. 17/561,676 (2022): Optimizing deployment and security of microservices

Paritosh Saxena, **Anjo Lucas Vahldiek-Oberwagner**, Mona Vij, Kshitij A Doshi, Carlos H Morales, Clair Bowman, Marcela S Melara, Michael Steiner

US Patent App. 17/314,349 (2021): TECHNOLOGY TO CONTROL SYSTEM CALL INVOCATIONS WITHIN A SINGLE ADDRESS SPACE

Michael Lemay, Anjo Vahldiek-Oberwagner

US Patent App. 17/131,716 (2021): Reducing latency of hardware trusted execution environments

Anjo Lucas Vahldiek-Oberwagner, Ravi L Sahita, Mona Vij, Rameshkumar Illikkal, Michael Steiner, Thomas Knauth, Dmitrii Kuvaiskii, Sudha Krishnakumar, Krystof C Zmudzinski, Vincent Scarlata, Francis McKeen

US Patent App. 17/131,684 (2021): Scalabe attestation for trusted execution environments

Anjo Lucas Vahldiek-Oberwagner, Ravi L Sahita, Mona Vij, Dayeol Lee, Haidong Xia, Rameshkumar Illikkal, Samuel Ortiz, Kshitij Arun Doshi, Mourad Cherfaoui, Andrzej Kuriata, Teck Joo Goh

US Patent App. 17/131,751 (2021): Isolating memory within trusted execution environments

Ravi L Sahita, **Anjo Lucas Vahldiek-Oberwagner**, Teck Joo Goh, Rameshkmar Illikkal, Andrzej Kuriata, Vedvyas Shanbhogue, Mona Vij, Haidong Xia

US Patent 9,165,155 (2015): Protecting the integrity and privacy of data with storage leases Peter Druschel, Rodrigo Rodrigues, Ansley Post, Johannes Gehrke, **Anjo Lucas Vahldiek**

Talks

MeSHwA: The case for a Memory-Safe Software and Hardware Architecture for Serverless Computing

Anjo Vahldiek-Oberwagner

WORDS Workshop 2022

Breaking with traditional OS Abstractions

Anjo Vahldiek-Oberwagner

Guest Lecture for Operating System class at IIT Kharagpur in 2021

Tutorial: Graphene: Confidential Computing for Unmodified Linux Applications

Anjo Vahldiek-Oberwagner, Chia-Che Tsai, Dmitrii Kuvaiskii, Don Porter

IEEE Secure Development Conference (SecDev) 2020

Automatically Securing Linux Application Containers in Untrusted Clouds

Anjo Vahldiek-Oberwagner, Dmitrii Kuvaiskii

Linux Security Summit, Refereed Presentation, 2020

ERIM: Secure, Efficient In-process Isolation with Memory Protection Keys

Anjo Vahldiek-Oberwagner USENIX Security, 2019

Enforcing Confidentiality and Integrity Policies over untrusted Applications

Anjo Vahldiek-Oberwagner

Intel Labs, 2016

Bell Labs, 2016

Guardat: Enforcing data policies at the Storage layer

Anjo Vahldiek-Oberwagner

EuroSys, 2015

Microsoft Research, 2014

Trusted Storage

Anjo Vahldiek-Oberwagner

USENIX FAST Conference Work in Progress, 2012

WiP/Posters

The Rise of Memory-Safe Languages: Building a Fast, Elastic, Secure Software & Hardware Architecture
Anjo Vahldiek-Oberwagner

DARPA Forward Conference as DARPA Riser 2022

Thoth: Efficiently enforcing data confidentiality and integrity in large-scale distributed data processing systems

Eslam Elnikety, Anjo Vahldiek, Aastha Mehta, Deepak Garg, Peter Druschel

ACM SOSP'13 Work in progress

Trusted Storage

Anjo Vahldiek, Eslam Elnikety, Ansley Post, Peter Druschel, Deepak Garg, Johannes Gehrke, Rodrigo

Rodrigues

Usenix FAST'12 Work in progress

Honors 2023 ASPLOS Distinguished Paper Award

& Awards 2022 Selected as DARPA Riser 2022, Topic: "The Rise of Memory-Safe Languages: Building a Fast, Elastic,

Secure Software & Hardware Architecture"

2021 Intel High-5 Patent Award

2021 Intel Labs Gordy Award Honorable Mention in "Excelence in Risk Taking" for our

continued work on the Graphene Library OS (in collaboration with Dmitrii Kuvaiskii, Mona Vii,

Sudha Krishnakumar, Isaku Yamahata)

2019 USENIX and Facebook Internet Defense Prize 2019 USENIX Security Distinguished Paper Award 2010-2016 Max Planck Society, PhD Scholarship

2009 Saarland University, Graduate School PhD Scholarship

2007 IBM International Internship Scholarship

Program EuroSys'25 PC

Committee & USENIX Security'24 PC & Research Ethics Committee

Review ACM Conference on Reproducibility and Replicability'23 PC

Service USENIX Security'23 PC

USENIX Security'22 PC USENIX Security'21 PC

Middleware'20 Doctoral Workshop PC

EuroSys'20 ShadowPC SOCC'19 Poster PC

External reviewer EuroSys'18 External reviewer HotOS'17 External reviewer OSDI'16

Artifact USENIX Security'24 Artifact Evaluation co-chair **Evaluation** USENIX Security'23 Artifact Evaluation co-chair

Service EuroSys'22 Artifact Evaluation co-chair

SuperComputing'21 Artifact Evaluation co-chair

OSDI'20 Artifact Evaluation co-chair

USENIX Security'20 Artifact Evaluation Committee

SOSP'19 Artifact Evaluation Committee

Organization Steering committee of ACM Conference on Reproducibility and Replicability

Service & Steering committee of NSF Repeto Project **Activities** EuroSys'21 registration and finance co-chair

Co-Develop WelcomeHelp.de Refugee Volunteer Tool

Student Admission Volunteer MPI-SWS

General Student Meeting Coordinator MPI-SWS